Hi again. Now that you've
learned the key components for
organizing and facilitating
an effective team meeting,
we'll explore the
specifics of some of
the most common types of meetings
you'll need to have
during a project.
Every project has meetings,
lots of meetings.
While every meeting is unique,
being familiar with the
most common types of
project management meetings will
help you better
identify the goals,
structure, and activities
best suited for each one.
There are four general types
of project management meetings,
project kick-off, status updates,
stakeholder reviews,
and project reviews.
The first one we'll talk about
is the project kick-off meeting.
This is often considered the
official beginning of
a project and serves
as a way to align the
team's understanding of
the project goals with
actual plans and procedures.
Members of your team are
the major attendees of
your kickoff meeting.
But the participation of
senior management and
key stakeholders is also
required for securing buy-in and
ensuring alignment
with project goals.
The next type of
meeting we'll discuss,
are status update meetings.
Status update meetings are one of
the most common
types of meetings.
This category includes
regular team meetings
where the primary goal is to
align the team on updates,
progress, challenges,
and next steps.
During the meeting,
the project manager
may distribute or present
project performance
reports and formal
status updates on key
elements of the project.
This allows the team and
stakeholders to gain
visibility into current
performance levels
and task progress.
One of the project manager's
key responsibilities
is to be aware of the
status of the project at
any given time and to
ensure that others are
up to speed or know where to
find the latest information.
In order to do that,
status updates become a
critical tool throughout
the life cycle of a project
to check in on the project.
Typically, you'll
assess the status of
each of the following
topics during this meeting.
First, are task updates.
It is important for
the attendees to know,
what is the status of
the most urgent tasks?
How many tasks have
been completed,
and how many open items remain?
Next, is schedule status.
Are we behind schedule?
Ahead of schedule? Or on
pace with our projections?
Similarly, it's common to discuss
the budget status and
any new items that
impact your bottom line.
Then you should discuss
current or anticipated issues.
For example, changes, risks,
resource issues, vendor
issues, and so on.
Particularly changes
to quality and scope.
It's always a good idea to raise
these items on a recurring basis
so that no one is
caught off guard
and you can discuss
solutions together.
Lastly, you'll want to
discuss action items.
An action item is a task on
your list that needs
to be completed.
Assigning action items is
a great way to wrap up
the meeting and make sure
the project keeps forging ahead.
Remember, every action item
has an owner and a due date.
The status meeting is
a fundamental project tool
that keeps the project on track.
Most project managers
recommend using
a relatively fixed agenda
and time with this meeting.
To keep the team engaged,
follow the agenda, and hold
the meeting to a tight schedule.
Because the project
manager should
be able to report up-to-date
information to the
project sponsors
or clients at any time,
it's important to conduct
status meetings regularly.
Status meetings are
beneficial because they
provide an opportunity for
recognizing milestones,
sharing information, and
raising concerns to the team.
How often you decide to schedule
these meetings depends
on several factors,
such as the project's complexity,
number of team members,
and the level of
information required by
the project sponsor,
clients, or others.
Don't be afraid to change up
the cadence as your
project progresses.
Another type of project
management meeting,
is a stakeholder meeting.
Stakeholder engagement
is essential
for a successful
project management.
The goal of a stakeholder meeting
is to get buy-in and support.
Stakeholders, each
have their own set
of tools, know-how,
and expertise.
Stakeholder meetings are where
these contributions are
outlined and utilized.
You'll need to start
by understanding
a stakeholder's
challenges or problems.
Then respond accordingly and make
necessary adjustments to
resolve those challenges.
Winning and sustaining
the support of
your stakeholders is important
to your project's success.
In some cases, you
might want to have
stakeholder meetings
on a one-on-one basis.
This allows you to dive deeper on
relevant details with
each stakeholder.
Then you can cover the
topics that are most
interesting and concerning
to that particular person.
Other times you'll need to
engage stakeholders in groups.
If you have a large number
of stakeholders to manage,
focus the meeting on
your project's most
influential stakeholders.
Identify appropriate stakeholders
for high touch communication.
For example, you may
focus the meeting on
senior managers from each of
the groups you need to engage.
Other stakeholders can be
informed using other methods,
such as email or meeting notes.
While there are a number of
potential topics to cover when
meeting with stakeholders,
most meetings are limited
to communicating
critical information.
You should always be able to
present a project update.
Start the meeting with
a short overall project's
status update of 2-5 minutes.
Another key reason to
meet with stakeholders is
to seek out and
listen to feedback.
Or you might meet with
stakeholders to make
a decision or resolve
a major issue surrounding
your project.
In this case, you'll
often meet with
senior leaders and
the project sponsor.
Decisions could include go,
or no-go decisions, a
choice between options,
or signing off on investments.
Stakeholder meetings are
generally more formal.
It's normal to prepare
reading materials and
documents to review
ahead of time to help get people
in the right mindset
for the meeting.
Stakeholder meetings can
be regular and recurring,
or just a one-off
project meeting.
The frequency will depend on why
the stakeholder is
involved in the project.
Are they playing an advisory role
such as a consultant in a RACI,
or just someone to inform
and keep in the loop?
Does their involvement
center around
just one activity on the project,
or do they need to stay involved
on a longer-term basis?
You'll need to decide on
a case-by-case basis.
The end of the project or the
end of the project phase is
an excellent opportunity to
review how the project unfolded.
This is called a retrospective,
and you'll learn
more about this in
other sections of this course.
A typical retrospective
meeting agenda
includes reviewing
lessons learned
about what's going well,
what you should keep doing,
and what can be improved.
Equally important to
reviewing lessons learned is
taking the opportunity to
celebrate the project's success.
Knowing the difference between
these project meeting
types allows you
to maximize productivity and
ensure that you're
not wasting time.
You'll get the right outcome
for each type of meeting,
which will help
drive decisions and
lead to proactive
positive actions.
Amazing, you just learned
about the common types of
project meetings and how to make
them effective for
everyone in the room.
In the next video,
we'll recap what
you've learned in
the past few videos.
I'll meet you there.